A Register of the Claude Paillat Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Claude Paillat papers
1863-2000
2008C38
Paillat, Claude
Number of Containers: 435 manuscript boxes, 14 card file boxes, 4 oversize boxes 183.7 linear feet
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Acquired in 2008, the Claude Paillat papers in the Hoover Institution Archives represent a substantial documentary resource on modern French history. At present, they are the single largest collection relating to France in the holdings of the archives. The large bulk of the papers is comprised of the research materials used by Paillat in the preparation of his books on France during the period between the end of World War I and the aftermath of World War II. There are additional materials relating to the wars in Indochina and Algeria; to the local and regional history of 20th century France; to the presidencies of Charles de Gaulle, Georges Pompidou, Valéry Giscard d'Estaing, and François Mitterrand; and to French economic history.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2008.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1924 Born, Paris, France
1949-1956 Journalist, Paris Match. Reports on wars in Indochina and Algeria
1958-1961 Journalist, Paris-Presse
1961 Author, Dossier secret de l'Algérie
1961-1985 Journalist, Le Canard enchaîné
1966 Author, l'échiquier de l'Algérie
1969 Author, Archives secrètes 1968-1969: les coulisses d'une année terrible Author, 20 ans qui déchirent la France, tome 1. Le Guêpier
1972 Author, 20 ans qui déchirent la France, tome 2. La Liquidation
1979 Author, Dossiers secrets de la France, tome 1. 1919 ou les illusions de la gloire
1980 Author, Dossiers secrets de la France, tome 2. La Victoire perdue
1981 Author, Dossiers secrets de la France, tome 3. La Guerre à l'horizon
1983-1984 Author, Dossiers secrets de la France, tome 4. Le Désastre de 1940 (in two volumes)
1985 Author, Dossiers secrets de la France, tome 5. La Guerre-éclair
1987 Author, Dossiers secrets de la France, tome 6. L'Occupation, le pillage de la France
1989 Author, Dossiers secrets de la France, tome 7. La France dans la guerre américaine
1992 Author, Dossiers secrets de la France, tome 8. Le monde sans la France
2001 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
Acquired in 2008, the Claude Paillat papers in the Hoover Institution Archives represent a substantial documentary resource on modern French history. At present, they are the single largest collection relating to France in the holdings of the archives. The large bulk of the papers is comprised of the research materials used by Paillat in the preparation of his books on France during the period between the end of World War I and the aftermath of World War II. There are additional materials relating to the wars that ended French colonial rule in Indochina and Algeria; to the local and regional history of 20th century France; to the presidencies of Charles de Gaulle, Georges Pompidou, Valéry Giscard d'Estaing, and François Mitterrand; and to French economic history.
Paillat was a journalist who became a best-selling historian. His most significant work is his eight-volume Dossiers secrets de la France contemporaine, a series that covers the span of French history from the conclusion of the First World War to the end of the Second. He also published a two-volume study of the Algerian War; a monograph on the French defeat in Indochina, as well as one on the last turbulent year of Charles de Gaulle's presidency; and a two part history of the Catholic church in France.
Paillat's books enjoyed popular success while at the same time being based on exhaustive research. He not only made use of various French archives, he also relied on the extensive contacts he had made across French society, including members of the military, leading industrialists, and politicians. These contacts allowed Paillat to consult, and in some cases acquire, personal collections of correspondence and other documents, many of which formed the basis of the detailed descriptions of events and personalities in his books. His exclusive access to such documents also give Paillat's books - most of which contain the word "secret" in the title - the aspect of revealing confidential or privileged information. Paillat referred to his research methods as yielding a "tapestry" woven from various sources.
The Research Materials are arranged according to Paillat's original French subject headings, with additional identification provided at the folder level. The materials include copies of many official documents, private correspondence, as well as clippings and academic studies. There are numerous military records - intelligence reports, campaign journals and correspondence - relating to the French experience in World War II. There are also many documents generated by the French national police (Gendarmerie Nationale) during the Vichy period. Additionally, there are copies of reports on France in the 1930s originating from the United States embassy in Paris, as well as other American documents concerning France and North Africa in World War II.
The Paillat papers contain substantial materials emanating from the French colonial administrations in Indochina and North Africa. The Indochina materials span the period from the 1920s to the French defeat at Dien Bien Phu, and include some documents describing the increasing American involvement in Vietnam in the 1950s. There are extensive materials in the collection pertaining to the Algerian War, including many documents relating both to the Algerian nationalist movement and the military rebellion by rightwing French officers against de Gaulle. There are also many police and intelligence reports from Algeria in the 1920s and 1930s.
The research materials are particularly rich in the local and regional history of France. Paillat was interested in documenting the family histories of the French economic elite (patronat) and conducted many interviews with members of this social class. The collection has numerous tape recordings and transcripts of these interviews. There is extensive documentation of the interwar years in France, on domestic politics and little studied movements such as Bourgeoisie Chrétienne, Redressement Français, and X-Crise. There are also materials relating to various social reform initiatives in France, including documents acquired by Paillat from the personal collections of Aymé Bernard and Achille Liénart.
The Paillat papers contain press accounts and leaflets pertaining to the protest movement of French students and workers in May-June 1968. There are also significant materials on the years following de Gaulle's resignation as president, including the Mitterrand era. These largely relate to French political parties, election campaigns, and a number of public scandals involving allegations of corruption and bribery.
The Correspondence series contains a large general file that is arranged chronologically. This consists largely of letters received by Paillat from the readers of his books, as well as a considerable number of letters from the contacts who provided him information and documents in aid of his research.
The Writings series of the papers contain the drafts of many of Paillat's books, as well as his correspondence with his publishers, readers, and those sources who had provided him with information and documents for the writing of his books. In this series, there are also numerous articles written by Paillat during his career as a journalist for the newspaper, Le Canard enchaîné. The articles focus on French politics as well reporting on business trends among French media companies.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
World War, 1939-1945 France.; France--History--1914-1940.; France--History--German occupation, 1940-1945.; France--History--1945-1958.; France--History--1958-; France--Politics and government--20th century.; France--Economic conditions--20th century.; France--Colonies.
Collection Contents
- Research materials, 1863-1999 (Folder 1-414)
  Contains bulletins, clippings, correspondence, reports, serial issues, sound recordings, transcripts of interviews, arranged by subject
  - Addresses, 1970-1980 (Folder 253-254)
  - Affairs politiques, 1969-1982 (Folder 45-48)
    - Affaire Aranda, 1972-1974 (Folder 45: 11)
    - Affaires Attia et Augé, 1971-1973 (Folder 45: 12)
    - Affaire Boulin, 1979-1980 (Folder 45: 13)
    - Affaire de Broglie, 1980 (Folder 45: 14)
    - Affaire de Vathaire/Dassault, 1976-1977 (Folder 46: 1)
    - Affaire Dega, 1971-1974 (Folder 46: 2)
    - Affaire Gorel, 1972 (Folder 46: 3)
    - Affaire Guérini, 1970-1978 (Folder 46: 4)
    - Affaire Marchais, 1977-1980 (Folder 46: 5)
    - Affaire Markovic, 1970-1975 (Folder 46: 6)
    - Affaire Modiano, 1972-1973 (Folder 46: 7)
    - Affaire Papillon, 1969-1970 (Folder 46: 8)
    - Affaire Stehlin, 1974-1975 (Folder 46: 9)
    - Affaire Susini, 1970 (Folder 46: 10)
    - Service d'Action Civique, 1981-1982 (Folder 46: 11)
    - Vol d'armes de Foix, 1981-1982 (Folder 46: 12)
    - Affaire Lucet, 1982 (Folder 46: 13)
    - Écoutes téléphoniques, 1970-1975 (Folder 47: 1)
    - Attentats d'Orly, 1975 (Folder 47: 2)
    - Attentat à Neuilly, 1980 (Folder 47: 3)
    - Douaniers arrêtés en Suisse, 1980 (Folder 47: 4)
    - l'Étoile, 1970-1971 (Folder 47: 5)
    - Affaire Lascorz, 1972-1973 (Folder 47: 6)
    - la Défense, 1976-1979 (Folder 47: 7)
    - Centre Georges Pompidou, 1976-1979 (Folder 47: 8)
    - la Villette, 1969-1978 (Folder 47: 9)
    - les Halles, 1969-1979 (Folder 47: 10)
    - Affaire des diamants, 1979-1980 (Folder 47: 11)
    - Mystère Fontanet, 1980 (Folder 47: 12)
    - Pots-de-vin, 1972-1976 (Folder 47: 13)
    - Garantie foncière, 1971-1974 (Folder 47: 14)
    - Patrimoine foncier, 1971-1976 (Folder 48: 1)
    - Vedettes de Cherbourg, 1969-1970 (Folder 48: 2)
    - Affaire Chaban-Delmas, 1971-1973 (Folder 48: 3)
  - Agendas, 1965-1985 (Folder 276-277)
  - Afrique du Nord, 1942-1953 (Folder 276-277)
    - Problème colonial, 1942-1945 (Folder 91)
      - 1942 (Folder 91: 5)
      - 1943 (Folder 91: 6)
      - 1944 (Folder 91: 7)
      - 1945 (Folder 91: 8)
    - Commandos nord-africains, 1953 (Folder 91: 9)
  - Agriculture et industrie, 1920-1937 (Folder 221)
    - Clémentel, Étienne, 1920 (Folder 221: 1)
    - Société des Nations, 1930-1931 (Folder 221: 2-3)
    - Crise économique mondiale, 1931-1932 (Folder 221: 4)
    - Coût de la vie, 1932 (Folder 221: 5-6)
    - Matières premières, 1937 (Folder 221: 7)
    - Crise agricole, 1931 (Folder 221: 8)
    - Situation et organisation de l'agriculture, 1931 (Folder 221: 9)
    - Surproduction agricole, 1931 (Folder 221: 10)
    - Blé, 1931-1933 (Folder 221: 11-18)
    - Vin, 1932 (Folder 221: 19)
    - Rapports et notes sur l'agriculture, 1934-1937 (Folder 221: 20-23)
  - Alibert, Raphaël, 1928-1975 (Folder 350)
    - Entretien avec Jacques Alibert, 1973 (Folder 350: 8)
    - Élections législatives, 1928 (Folder 350: 9)
    - Note de M. Renaudin, 1970 (Folder 350: 10)
    - Affinités françaises, 1934-1935 (Folder 350: 11)
    - Entretien avec M. Artur, 1975 (Folder 350: 12)
  - Alsace, 1968-1976 (Folder 163: 12)
  - Algérie I, 1943-1948 (Folder 91-92)
    - Générale, 1943-1945 (Folder 91: 10)
    - Évènements de Constantine et de Sétif, 1945 (Folder 91: 11-12)
    - Réformes, 1944 (Folder 92: 1)
    - Situation politque, 1946-1948 (Folder 92)
      - 1946 (Folder 92: 2)
      - 1947 (Folder 92: 3-4)
      - 1948 (Folder 92: 5-6)
  - Algérie I, 1919-1967 (Folder 303-306)
    - Mouvement National Algérien, 1955 (Folder 303: 14)
    - Front de l'Algérie Française, 1960 (Folder 303: 15)
    - Organisation Armée Secrète (O.A.S.), 1961-1967 (Folder 304)
      - 1961 (Folder 304: 1)
      - 1962 (Folder 304: 2-3)
      - 1967 (Folder 304: 4)
    - Indigènes, 1919-1921 (Folder 304)
      - 1919 (Folder 304: 5-8)
      - 1920 (Folder 304: 9)
      - 1921 (Folder 304: 10)
    - Renseignements Généraux, 1950-1952 (Folder 305)
      - 1950 (Folder 305: 1)
      - 1951 (Folder 305: 3-8)
      - 1952 (Folder 305: 9, Folder 306: 1)
  - Algérie II, 1921-1923 (Folder 35)
    - 1921 (Folder 35: 5-7)
    - 1922 (Folder 35: 8)
    - 1923 (Folder 35: 9)
  - Algérie II, 1946-1961 (Folder 121-122)
    - Chronologie, 1955-1961 (Folder 121: 13)
    - Dispositif de Protection Urbaine, 1957-1958 (Folder 121: 14)
    - Renseignements Généraux, 1946-1951 (Folder 122)
      - Générale, 1948-1951 (Folder 122: 1)
      - Situation politique, 1946 (Folder 122: 2)
      - Police, 1948 (Folder 122: 3)
      - Situation des nord-africains dans la métropole, 1950-1951 (Folder 122: 4)
  - Algérie II, 1949-1955 (Folder 185)
    - 1949 (Folder 185: 1)
    - 1950 (Folder 185: 2)
    - 1951 (Folder 185: 3)
    - 1952 (Folder 185: 4)
    - 1953 (Folder 185: 5)
    - 1954 (Folder 185: 6-7)
    - 1955 (Folder 185: 8)
  - Algérie III, 1924-1956 (Folder 122-123)
    - Situation économique, politique et sociale, 1924-1926 (Folder 122)
      - 1924 (Folder 122: 5)
      - 1925 (Folder 122: 6-7)
      - 1926 (Folder 122: 8)
    - Alger, 1924-1926 (Folder 122: 9)
    - Beyrouth, 1925 (Folder 122: 10)
    - Bourgoin, 1924 (Folder 122: 11)
    - Médéa, 1926 (Folder 122: 12)
    - Mzab, 1926 (Folder 122: 13)
    - Paris, 1924 (Folder 122: 14)
    - Argent saisi, 1956 (Folder 123: 1)
    - Benboulaid, Mostefa, 1956 (Folder 123: 2)
    - Ighil Imoula, 1956 (Folder 123: 3)
    - Mollet, Guy, 1956 (Folder 123: 4)
    - Papon, Maurice, 1956 (Folder 123: 5)
    - Libérations proposées, 1956 (Folder 123: 6)
    - Programme, 1956 (Folder 123: 7)
    - Syndicats, 1956 (Folder 123: 8)
    - Tebessa, 1956 (Folder 123: 9)
  - Algérie III, 1959-1960 (Folder 185)
    - l'Africain, 1959-1962 (Folder 185)
      - 1959-1960 (Folder 185: 9)
      - 1961-1962 (Folder 185: 10)
    - Paris-presse-l'intransigeant, 1959-1960 (Folder 186)
      - 1959 (Folder 186: 1-2)
      - 1960 (Folder 186: 3-4)
  - Algérie IV, 1928-1929 (Folder 186)
    - Générale, 1929 (Folder 186: 5)
    - Alger, 1928-1929 (Folder 186: 6)
    - Paris, 1929 (Folder 186: 7)
  - Algérie IV, 1946-1971 (Folder 123-124)
    - Générale, 1960 (Folder 123: 10)
    - Amnisties, 1962 (Folder 123: 11)
    - Arrestations et tortures, 1962-1964 (Folder 123: 12)
    - Cartes de presse, 1956-1959 (Folder 123: 13)
    - l'Église et l'Algérie, 1962 (Folder 123: 14)
    - Enlèvements, 1962-1968 (Folder 123: 15)
    - Franc-maçonnerie, 1948 (Folder 124: 1)
    - Frères musulmans, 1966 (Folder 124: 2)
    - Pétrole, 1958-1971 (Folder 124: 3)
    - Plein emploi et migration, 1946-1950 (Folder 124: 4)
    - Tracts, 1959-1960 (Folder 124: 5)
  - Algérie IV, 1957 (Folder 306)
    - Français-Juifs à Constantine, 1957 (Folder 306: 2)
    - Cessez-le-feu, 1957 (Folder 306: 3)
    - Criminalité algérienne, 1957 (Folder 306: 4)
    - Sammarcelli, 1957 (Folder 306: 5)
    - Tracts, 1957 (Folder 306: 6)
    - Mollet, Guy, 1957 (Folder 306: 7)
    - Attitude de la Tunisie, 1957 (Folder 306: 8)
    - Scelles, Jean, 1957 (Folder 306: 9)
    - Commandements civils et militaires, 1957 (Folder 306: 10)
    - Hamon, Léo, 1957 (Folder 306: 11)
    - Journalistes, 1957 (Folder 306: 12)
    - Statut, 1957 (Folder 306: 13)
    - Haleyi, Abderrahmane, 1957 (Folder 306: 14)
    - Section P, 1957 (Folder 306: 15)
    - Activité subversive, 1957 (Folder 306: 16)
    - Discours, 1957 (Folder 306: 17)
    - Sétif, 1957 (Folder 306: 18-19)
    - Projet loi-cadre, 1957 (Folder 306: 20)
    - Aurès'opérations et exécutions sommaires, 1957 (Folder 306: 21)
    - Bataille d'Alger, 1957 (Folder 306: 22)
  - Algérie V, 1930-1931 (Folder 230-231)
    - Générale, 1930-1931 (Folder 230-231)
      - 1930 (Folder 230: 19)
      - 1931 (Folder 230: 20)
    - Voyage présidentiel, 1930 (Folder 230: 21)
    - Conférence Nord-Africaine, 1930 (Folder 230: 22-12)
    - Graphiques, 1930 (Folder 230: 24)
    - Centenaire, 1930 (Folder 230: 25)
    - Renseignements, 1930 (Folder 230: 26-28)
    - Parti Communiste, 1930 (Folder 230: 29-31)
    - Rapport sur la situation politique et administrative des indigènes, 1931 (Folder 231: 1)
    - Ain-Bessem, 1930 (Folder 231: 2)
    - Ain-Sefra, 1930 (Folder 231: 3-4)
    - Alger, 1930 (Folder 231: 5-17)
    - Bou-Denib, 1930 (Folder 231: 18)
    - Colomb-Béchar, 1930 (Folder 231: 19)
    - Dakar, 1930 (Folder 231: 20)
    - Oran, 1930 (Folder 231: 21)
    - Paris, 1930 (Folder 231: 22-23)
    - Siddi-Bel-Abbès, 1930 (Folder 231: 24)
  - Algérie V, 1931-1958 (Folder 204)
    - Rapports sur la situation politique des indigènes, 1931 (Folder 204: 4)
    - Alger, 1931-1932 (Folder 204: 5)
    - Paris, 1931-1932 (Folder 204: 6)
    - Rabat, 1932 (Folder 204: 7)
    - Rome, 1932 (Folder 204: 8)
    - Ordioni, Pierre, 1956-1958 (Folder 204: 9)
  - Algérie V, 1946-1967 (Folder 307-308)
    - Élections, 1947 (Folder 307: 1)
    - Gaulle, Charles de, 1947 (Folder 307: 2)
    - Partis politiques, 1946-1947 (Folder 307: 3)
    - Tubert, Paul, 1947 (Folder 307: 4)
    - Économie, 1947 (Folder 307: 5)
    - Élections, 1948-1949 (Folder 307: 6)
    - Parti Communiste Algérien, 1947-1949 (Folder 307: 7)
    - Parti du Peuple Algérien, 1947-1949 (Folder 307: 8)
    - Socialistes, 1949 (Folder 307: 9)
    - Union des Femmes d'Algérie, 1947 (Folder 307: 10)
    - Chataigneau, Yves, 1945 (Folder 307: 11)
    - Arnould, Auguste, 1959 (Folder 307: 12)
    - Biaggi, Jean-Baptiste, 1960 (Folder 307: 13)
    - Bigeard, Marcel, 1961 (Folder 307: 14)
    - Maroc, 1956 (Folder 308: 1-2)
    - Byr, Albert, 1967 (Folder 308: 3)
    - Challe, Maurice, 1958-1961 (Folder 308: 4)
  - Algérie V, 1958 (Folder 175-176)
    - Bourguiba, Habib, 1958 (Folder 175: 9)
    - Algérie nouvelle, 1958 (Folder 175: 10)
    - Sakiet, 1958 (Folder 175: 11)
    - Gaulle, Charles de, 1958 (Folder 175: 12)
    - Élections, 1958 (Folder 175: 13)
    - Études de la Délégation Générale, 1958 (Folder 175: 14)
    - Plan de Constantine, 1958 (Folder 175: 15)
    - Rapports, 1958 (Folder 176: 1)
    - Favre, Jean, 1958 (Folder 176: 2)
    - Kabylie, 1958 (Folder 176: 3)
    - Delbecque, Léon, 1958 (Folder 176: 4)
    - Comité de Salut Public, 1958 (Folder 176: 5)
  - Algérie VI, 1933-1936 (Folder 124-125)
    - Générale, 1933-1936 (Folder 124)
      - 1933 (Folder 124: 6)
      - 1934 (Folder 124: 7)
    - Politique indigène, 1934-1936 (Folder 124: 8)
    - Aïn-M'lila, 1933 (Folder 124: 9)
    - Alger, 1933 (Folder 124: 10)
    - Batna, 1933 (Folder 124: 11)
    - Colomb-Béchar, 1933 (Folder 124: 12)
    - Constantine, 1933-1935 (Folder 124: 13)
    - Oran, 1933 (Folder 124: 14)
    - Ouargla, 1933 (Folder 124: 15)
    - Paris, 1933 (Folder 125: 1)
    - Rome, 1933 (Folder 125: 2)
    - Territoires du Sud, 1933 (Folder 125: 3)
    - Touggourt, 1933 (Folder 125: 4)
    - Propagande communiste soviétique, 1933 (Folder 125: 5)
  - Algérie VI, 1940-1941 (Folder 114-115)
    - Rapports, 1940-1941 (Folder 114)
      - 1940 (Folder 114: 12)
      - 1941 (Folder 114: 13-14)
    - Notes du Général Maxime Weygand, 1940-1941 (Folder 115)
      - 1940 (Folder 115: 1)
      - 1941 (Folder 115: 2-4)
  - Algérie VI, 1959-1961 (Folder 360-361)
    - 1959 (Folder 360: 9)
    - 1960 (Folder 360: 10)
    - 1961 (Folder 361: 1-2)
  - Algérie VII, 1934 (Folder 125)
    - Générale, 1934 (Folder 125: 6)
    - Évènements de Constantine, 1934 (Folder 125: 7)
    - Alger, 1934 (Folder 125: 8)
    - Lyon, 1934 (Folder 125: 9)
    - Paris, 1934 (Folder 125: 10)
  - Algérie VII, 1956-1960 (Folder 182)
    - Dumont, Claude, 1960 (Folder 182: 5)
    - Gaulle, Charles de, 1960 (Folder 182: 6)
    - Lacoste, Robert, 1956-1958 (Folder 182)
      - 1956 (Folder 182: 7)
      - 1957-1958 (Folder 182: 8)
    - Tracts du Mouvement National de la Libération, 1956 (Folder 182: 9)
    - Service de presse, 1956 (Folder 182: 10-11)
  - Algérie VII, 1956-1963 (Folder 361)
    - Chaussade, Pierre, 1956-1958 (Folder 361: 3)
    - Cherrière, Paul, 1954-1955 (Folder 361)
      - 1954 (Folder 361: 4)
      - 1955 (Folder 361: 5-7)
    - Paillard, Jacques, 1963 (Folder 361: 8)
  - Algérie VII, 1962-1972 (Folder 273)
    - Massacres à Oran, 1962-1971 (Folder 273: 1)
    - Debré, Michel, 1962 (Folder 273: 2)
    - Coll, Giselle, 1972 (Folder 273: 3)
    - Cros, Vitalis, 1962 (Folder 273: 4)
    - Coupures de presse, 1962 (Folder 273: 5)
    - Massacre d'Alger, 1962 (Folder 273: 6)
    - France Presse-Action, 1962-1963 (Folder 273: 7)
    - Caserne Toiras, Saint-Martin-de-Ré, 1964 (Folder 273: 8)
  - Algérie VIII-Évènements de Constantine, 1934 (Folder 273: 9-11)
  - Algérie VIII (Folder 395)
    - Générale, 1962-1963 (Folder 395: 8)
    - Évènements de Constantine, 1964 (Folder 395: 9-10)
  - Algérie IX, 1934 (Folder 115)
    - Propagande, 1934 (Folder 115: 5)
    - Pétrole, 1934 (Folder 115: 6)
    - Évènements de Constantine, 1934 (Folder 115)
      - Générale, 1934 (Folder 115: 7)
      - Rapport de la commission d'enquête, 1934 (Folder 115: 8)
      - Situation économique, 1934 (Folder 115: 9)
      - Surveillance politique, 1934 (Folder 115: 10)
  - Algérie X, 1935 (Folder 125-126)
    - Générale, 1935 (Folder 125: 11-12)
    - Alger, 1935 (Folder 125: 13-15)
    - Batna, 1935 (Folder 126: 1)
    - Biskra, 1935 (Folder 126: 2)
    - Constantine, 1935 (Folder 126: 3)
    - Ghardaïa, 1935 (Folder 126: 4)
    - Guelma, 1935 (Folder 126: 5)
    - Laghouat, 1935 (Folder 126: 6)
    - Mostaganem, 1935 (Folder 126: 7)
    - Oran, 1935 (Folder 126: 8)
    - Paris, 1935 (Folder 126: 9)
    - Tizi-Ouzou, 1935 (Folder 126: 10)
    - Touggourt, 1935 (Folder 126: 11)
    - Zeraïa, 1935 (Folder 126: 12)
  - Algérie X, 1955-1964 (Folder 187)
    - Lagaillarde, P., 1961 (Folder 187: 1)
    - Lambert, Gabriel, 1955-1960 (Folder 187: 2)
    - Rapport du préfet Maisonneuve, 1956 (Folder 187: 3)
    - Martel, Robert, 1960 (Folder 187: 4)
    - Noel, André, 1961-1964 (Folder 187: 5)
  - Algérie XI, 1935-1936 (Folder 126)
    - Générale, 1935-1936 (Folder 126)
      - 1935 (Folder 126: 13)
      - 1936 (Folder 126: 14)
    - Évènements de Syrie, 1936 (Folder 126: 15)
    - Agitation communiste, 1936 (Folder 126: 16)
    - Alger, 1935-1936 (Folder 126: 17)
    - Batna, 1936 (Folder 126: 18)
    - Canrobert, 1936 (Folder 126: 19)
    - Constantine, 1936 (Folder 126: 20)
    - Mascara, 1936 (Folder 126: 21)
    - Mostaganem, 1936 (Folder 126: 22)
    - Oran, 1936 (Folder 126: 23)
    - Paris, 1936 (Folder 126: 24)
    - Philippeville, 1936 (Folder 126: 25)
    - Sétif, 1936 (Folder 126: 26)
    - Tlemcen, 1936 (Folder 126: 27)
  - Algérie XI, 1953-1971 (Folder 274)
    - Robin, Georges, 1961 (Folder 274: 1)
    - Salan, Raoul, 1958-1964 (Folder 274: 2)
    - Soustelle, Jacques, 1955-1960 (Folder 274: 3)
    - Brothier, Albert, 1971 (Folder 274: 4)
    - Parlange, Georges, 1953-1957 (Folder 274: 5)
  - Algérie XI, 1936 (Folder 127)
    - Générale, 1936 (Folder 127: 1)
    - Communistes, 1936 (Folder 127: 2)
    - Affreville, 1936 (Folder 127: 3)